Guide to the Edwin J. Beinecke Collection of Robert Louis Stevenson
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Manuscripts, 1828-1960; Series II; 13.35; (34 boxes)
  - Manuscripts by Robert Louis Stevenson
    - ["My love was warm..."], poem (6609), 1886 March (Box 34, Folder 810)
    - ["My narrow chamber fronts with many panes..."], poem (6611), undated (Box 34, Folder 811)
    - "My Ship and I," poem and song (6615-6617), undated (Box 34, Folder 812)
    - ["My summer health has gone away..."], poem (6618), undated
    - "My Wife," poem (6619), undated
    - "My Wife and I, in One Romantic Cot," poem (6620-6621), undated
    - ["Nay, but I fancy somehow year by year..."] (6622), [1880]
    - New Arabian Nights, notes (6626), undated (Box 34, Folder 813)
    - "The New House," poem (6628-6629), undated (Box 34, Folder 814)
    - "A Night in France," poem (6631), undated (Box 34, Folder 815)
    - ["Nor judge me light, tho' light at times I seem..."] (6633), 1872
    - ["Nor yet with empty hands! My ancestors..."], poem (6634), undated (Box 34, Folder 816)
    - "Not I" (6635-6636), undated
    - ["Not undelightful friend our rustic ease..."], poem (6637-6638), 1872, undated
    - "A Note at Sea" (6640), [1875] (Box 34, Folder 817)
    - [Notebooks]
      - "51", undated (Box 34, Folder 818)
        ["The birds shall sing..."] (6017)
        ["For there before your eyes..."] (6235)
        ["The hour shall...before the sun..."] (6320)
        ["I heard the doves..."] (6350)
        ["I saw the fair...rising out and in..."] (6361)
        ["If in the West my books are read..."] (6389)
        Kidnapped, dedication (6479)
        "The Merry Men and Other Tales and Fables," dedication (6576)
        ["Once there was a maid, a fairer maid than any..."] (6690)
        ["Red, red apples on the orchard grass..."] (6783)
        ["The shadows running free along the hills..."] (6834)
        ["We knew you better, dear, than you believed..."] (7103)
        ["Where all day long..."] (7151)
        ["You shall see the fingers..."] (7201)
      - "52", undated (Box 34, Folder 819)
        [Cornwall and Mont St. Michel], notes (6121)
        "Edifying Letters of the Rutherford Family" (6184)
        [François Villon, Student, Poet and Housebreaker] (7086)
      - "53", undated (Box 34, Folder 820)
        ["And me, the wise of now..."] (5962)
        ["At night I leave my little bed..."] (5989)
        "Auld Reekie," poem (5994-5996)
        Catriona, table of contents (6076)
        ["For I think you may percieve..."] (6233)
        "The Foreigner at Home" (6237)
        [Hazlitt, William. Notes for Projected Biography] (6275)
        ["Here in the place of the snows..."] (6311)
        ["How tall the grass and daisies grow..."] (6324)
        [Linguistic Exercise] (6527)
        [Lists of Titles of Books, Essays, Etc. Written or Projected by R.L.S.] (6533)
        "The Merry Men," table of contents (6576)
        ["O come, and take the mask away..."] (6653)
        ["O to arise and travel far..."] (6667)
        ["It is my wish that Robert Louis Stevenson..."] (6701)
        [Stevenson at Play] (6916)
        ["When, years ago, in Greece I dwelt..."] (7149)
        ["Whiles frae the fishwife's causey rond..."] (7154)
        [Will] (7302)
        ["Ye chimney pots of London, the wind shall blow you down..."] (7190)
      - "54", undated (Box 34, Folder 821)
        ["Arise, he said, unfriended boy..."] (5974)
        "Clans and Septs," notes (6099)
        ["If it be true..."] (6390)
        ["Je cherche à acheter cher..."] (6474)
        ["My muse, who has been out of town..."] (6610)
        ["On the unquiet waters of the world..."] (6686)
        [The Transformation of the Highlands], table of contents (7055)
      - "55", [1871-1872] (Box 34, Folder 822)
        [God, how the old..."] (6259)
        [Legal Notes] (6502)
        ["The old, old song, I only wrote it..."] (6674)
        [Spitful and Coquettish Fancies] (6904-6906)
      - "56", [1872-1873] (Box 34, Folder 823)
        [Economics. Notes] (6183)
        ["I dream in class..."] (6335)
        [Mathematical Notes] (6571)
        ["Snell blows the east wind off the sea..."] (6871)
      - "57", [1870-1871?] (Box 34, Folder 824)
        "Endosmosis, Etc.", notes (6191)
        ["Here, in my bed..."] (6310)
        "Inscription for the Tankard of a Society Now Dissolved" (6453-6454)
        [Legal Notes] (6503)
        ["O friends, in this dark hour..."] (6658)
        ["Ordain that I some after year..."] (6698)
        ["Sir Wm to Park..."] (6860)
        ["So as I travel on to death..."] (6873)
        ["Well has thou... full..."] (7125)
        ["When the swallows go away..."] (7146)
      - "58"
      - "59", [1871]-1872 (Box 34, Folder 825)
        ["And all this is to me but a single wood..."] (5960)
        "Aphorisms" (5971)
        ["The deep grass sighed and rustled..."] (6150)
        ["Do with it as they will..."] (6160-6161)
        "Imaginary Conversations" (6400)
        "Intellectual Powers," outline (6457)
        [Legal Notes] (6504)
        ["Lo as the trodden violet, the sun..."] (6536)
        ["The ringing ice was smooth as air..."] (6792)
        ["This winter day the lighted sky..."] (6976)
      - "60", undated (Box 34, Folder 826)
        ["Come sit wi' me, my trusty friend..."] (6112)
        "Deacon Brodie," notes (6143)
        ["In the murkest o' a winter night..."] (6425)
        ["Like the chance spark a reveller lets..."] (6524)
        ["Pleasure of life what ist? Only..."] (6724)
        ["The strain creeps softly in and out..."] (6933)
        "To the Commissioners of Northern Lights" (7037)
        ["With song and dance and poured out wine..."] (7176)
      - "61", 1880, undated (Box 35, Folder 827)
        [Accounts] (5936)
        "Fate of the House," list (6216)
        ["I got your walie book yestreen..."] (6344)
        [Prince Otto Characters] (6742)
        ["S... with sherry..."] (6799)
      - "62", undated (Box 35, Folder 828)
        ["But star or compass far a-sea..."] (6059)
        ["Calumnious writers say that I..."] (6064)
        ["A fellow feeling makes us wondrous kind..."] (6220)
        [French History. Fifteenth Century], notes (6244)
        ["I am a letter in a tongue..."] (6327)
        ["I come, in hot reduplication..."] (6330)
        ["I was a Frenchman..."] (6369)
        [If I be neither ill nor well..."] (6384)
        ["A long time ago the world began..."] (6541)
        ["Mine be the lips..."] (6582)
        ["A modern Samuel, if the tale be true..."] (6586)
        ["My question now all spirits occupies..."] (6612)
        ["Promise from my... dear father to but..."] (6745)
      - "A 154", 1886 (Box 35, Folder 829)
        "The Counterblast--1886" (6123)
        "The Counterblast Ironical" (6125)
        "Independent Companies" (6450)
        ["It's an owercome sooth for age an' youth..."] (6469)
        ["It's something to be wrastled through..."] (6472)
        [List of Titles or First Lines of Poems of 18 Poems] (6532)
        "A Lowden Sabbath Morn," poem (6551)
        "Macgregors" (6554)
      - "A 155"
      - "A 159", [circa 1880-1881] (Box 35, Folder 830)
        "An Inquiry Into the Causes and Effects of Emigration from the Highlands..." (6460)
      - "A 161"
      - "A 255"
      - "A 264 A Early Notes"
      - "A 267 Essays and Verses (full)"
      - "A 269", undated (Box 35, Folder 831-832)
        ["At morning on the garden seat..."] (5988)
        [Brashiana 5] (6028); [Brashiana 9] (6033-6035); [Brashiana 10] (6038); [Brashiana 11] (6039-6041); [Brashiana 12] (6042-6043); [Brashiana 15] (6044); [Brashiana 16] (6045); [Brashiana 17] (6046-6047); [Brashiana 18] (6048)
        ["Breath not the name of him who adores you..."] (6050)
        "The Canoe Speaks" (6066)
        ["Dread was the day..."] (6166)
        ["I saw the plough go up and down..."] (6362)
        ["If I indeed have power to please..."] (6387)
        ["If somewhere on that barren shore..."] (6393)
        "The Land of Story-Books" (6488)
        ["Let not the glare of idle praises..."] (6512)
        "My Wife and I, in One Romantic Cot" (6621)
        "The Royal Fortune" (6798)
        ["See the bonny b... rin..."] (6832)
        ["Sheer oer the crystal battlements from morn..."] (6839)
        ["So as the spot be shady and airy..."] (6874)
        [Soul of Suffield] (6901)
        ["Those that returning to the city lead..."] (6978)
        Treasure Island, dedication and draft fragment (7059-7060)
        ["We dwell in these melodious days..."] (7097)
        ["Whether I now inhabit on the free untenantable alp..."] (7153)
        ["Wild was the night..."] (7159)
      - "The Academic Exercise Book", [1871-1872] (Box 35, Folder 833)
        ["All influences were in vain..."] (5951)
        ["All through the sultry day I chased..."] (5954)
        "Canon [?] of Historical Method" (6070)
        ["Earth sucks our services completely..."] (6177)
        "I Am a Hunchback, Yellow Faced" (6326)
        ["I look across the ocean..."] (6354)
        ["I travel patiently the town..."] (6368)
        ["It was in the earliest spring tide..."] (6468)
        ["Many a night in this high room..."] (6559)
        ["The moon is sinking..."] (6590)
        ["O Italy as I look back..."] (6660)
        ["The old chimaeras, old receipts..."] (6670)
        ["The orchards cluster round the town..."] (6697)
        ["This man and I knew each..."] (6973)
        ["Well I have named you my generals..."] (7126)
      - "Autograph Notebook", [circa 1875-1876] (Box 36, Folder 834)
        "Forest Notes" (6238)
      - "Beau Austin..." (6006), [1884?] (Box 36, Folder 835-837)
      - "Copy book", [1879?], undated (Box 36, Folder 838)
        ["I care not I if all the world stands still..."] (6329)
        ["I seek your Christ..."] (6364)
        ["My line if you love me now..."] (6608)
        [Ne sit ancellae tibi amor pudari] (6623)
        ["Now in the early winter weather..."] (6647)
        ["O dull cold northern sky..."] (6655)
        ["One man spends everything in brothels..."] (6694)
        "Stout Marches Lead to Certain Ends" (6930)
        ["The supreme trust of man, I hold..."] (6950)
        ["The tempest raves in street and lane..."] (6960)
        ["To you who sings sparrows..."] (7053)
        ["When the sparrows pipe and twitter..."] (7144)
        ["You, a young man! All jocund youth..."] (7196)
      - "Copy Books", [1866-1872], undated (Box 36, Folder 839-842)
        [Anstruther, Notes From, Etc.] (5969)
      - "Copy Books", [1866-1872], undated (Box 37, Folder 843-847)
        "Notes: Practical, Historical and Amusing" (6642)
      - "The Count's Secret, Etc", 1865 June 5 (Box 37, Folder 848)
        "Anagrams on Town in Asia" (5959)
        "Anecdote of a Sermon" (5965)
        "A Boy's Reminiscences of Mr. Cobden" (6023)
        "Charade" (6090)
        "The Convicts" (6120)
        "The Count's Secret" (6127)
      - "Early Verses, 1872, etc."
      - "First Drafts of Poems", undated (Box 38, Folder 849)
        ["About my fields..."] (5930)
        "The Adorner of the Uncomely" (5944-5945)
        "Afar Along the Throbbing Beach" (5947)
        "Audawcious Odyshes" (5993)
        ["A while you have passed among our seminude..."] (6000)
        "The Bour-Tree Den" (6022)
        "Bright is the Ring of Words" (6051)
        "The Daughter" (6139)
        ["Dear Bazett, take this nice edition..."] (6144)
        ["The doors are opened now..."] (6163)
        ["The doves were in the red wood..."] (6164)
        "Early in the Spring" (6175)
        "An End of Travel" (6189)
        "Evensong" (6200-6201)
        "The Far-Farers" (6215)
        "He Hears with Gladdened Heart" (6276-6277)
        ["He met me in the windy place..."] (6279)
        ["Hear the Tale of Gillehinde..."] (6285)
        ["I have been warm with the fires of the tent..."] (6348)
        ["I stood in the dark and trembled..."] (6367)
        [I who apollo sometime visited..."] (6373-6374)
        ["I will make you brooches..."] (6377)
        ["If not for good..."] (6391)
        ["If this were faith..."] (6395-6396)
        ["If we could go like a pair of lovers..."] (6397)
        ["In dreams, unhappy, I behold you stand..."] (6406)
        ["It is a dream that I hear..."] (6461)
        ["Lang and I were dressed in our Sunday's best..."] (6489)
        ["Late, O Miller..."] (6494)
        ["Let no sad [?] looks degrade my burial day..."] (6511)
        "The Master of the House Tusitala" (6565)
        "Mater Triumphans" (6568)
        "Mother and Daughter" (6593-6594)
        "Night Crawls" (6630)
        ["O England is the fine country..."] (6657)
        ["O green and warm..."] (6659)
        "The Old Lday" (6673)
        ["On the red hill of the flowers..."] (6685)
        ["Or stranger still; can understand..."] (6696)
        ["Over the land is April..."] (6707)
        ["Plain as the glistening planets shine..."] (6720)
        ["She rested by the Broken Brook..."] (6837)
        ["Sir, and my countryman, though I..."] (6857)
        ["The snoring conch, but not the war..."] (6872)
        "The Son" (6882-6883)
        "Spring Carol" (6909)
        ["The spring thats in the gardens..."] (6912)
        ["The stars of night no plainer shine..."] (6913)
        ["The sun and the loud rain here alternate..."] (6943)
        [To Teuila] (7033)
        ["To the maids of the village the buds of the hill..."] (7041)
        "Tropic Rain" (7064)
        "Wandering Willie" (7088)
        ["What glory for a boy of ten..."] (7134)
        ["When she is absent whom my heart adores..."] (7141)
        ["When the sun comes after rain..."] (7145)
        ["When the wind blows from the highlands..."] (7148)
      - "RLS/C", 1881, undated (Box 38, Folder 850)
        "Across the Road and Past the Dene" (5938)
        "All Is Not Gold That Glitters" (5952)
        ["As in their flight the birds of song..."] (5979)
        ["As to these vales the blackbirds came a while..."] (5985)
        "At the Sea-Side" (5990)
        "Bed in Summer" (6007)
        "Beside the Wall the River Ran" (6014)
        ["Brave ancient lads in musical centuries..."] (6049)
        ["Bring out the dolls, bring out the blocks..."] (6054)
        "Bull Hunt" (6068)
        ["The dog is barking loud and long..."] (6162)
        "Familiar Studies of Men and Books," dedication (6209)
        ["For laughing I very much vote..."] (6234)
        "Foreign Lands" (6236)
        "A Good Boy" (6261)
        "A Good Play" (6263)
        ["Gratitude indeed—in spite of all our supervision..."] (6264)
        "Half a Loaf is Better Than No Bread" (6272)
        ["Heaven hanging open in the skies..."] (6305)
        ["Here by the old oak, beneath the pine..."] (6308)
        ["Here, upon these white hills, I dwell..."] (6315)
        ["The hour is sick, the hour shall die..."] (6316)
        "The Hunt Interrupted" (6325)
        ["I fare in lands of sabbath observancy..."] (6342)
        ["I offer here an everlasting pleasure..."] (6356)
        ["I rose before they told me to..."] (6359)
        ["I went a-nutting all by myself..."] (6371)
        ["I wish I had the Lolly Pops..."] (6381)
        ["If that which should be is not..."] (6394)
        ["In all the tidy chemists' shops..."] (6404)
        ["In open house the Irish member cries..."] (6419)
        ["In still eternal slumber these repose..."] (6422)
        "The Iron Steed" (6459)
        ["It is age indeed that chills our fireplace..."] (6465)
        ["It is impossible to keep lines of rail..."] (6466)
        ["It's there that I was sick and sad..."] (6473)
        ["Jim would be a sailor..."] (6476)
        "The Land of Counterpane" (6486)
        "The Land of Nod" (6487)
        ["Let me begone..."] (6510)
        ["Let sleeping dogs lie..."] (6513)
        ["Look out, my friend, it's on the card..."] (6544)
        ["Marmoreal stillness in the hill..."] (6560)
        ["My dear papa must buy the cake..."] (6603)
        "My Shadow" (6613-6614)
        "My Ship and I" (6615)
        ["Now all the roads are full of mire..."] (6644)
        ["Now here we are again, my lads..."] (6646)
        ["O! cast it cheerly from you, this disease..."] (6652)
        ["Odonovan Rosa be damned..."] (6669)
        ["Once a week at candlelight..."] (6687)
        ["Once more snow terreted Davos..."] (6688)
        ["Our high, alfresco, alpine kind of life..."] (6703)
        [Pirate Story] (6718)
        ["The pleasant waters run, a shining in the sun..."] (6723)
        ["Plough land and lea, stubble and trees..."] (6725)
        ["A portion of the human frame..."] (6732)
        ["The rain is raining all around..."] (6747)
        ["Said Burton... to Colvin, said Colvin to Legros..."] (6800)
        ["Ships in bath tub..."] (6840)
        ["Sir and my friend, till winter comes again..."] (6858)
        ["Sir, while we tread the paths of day..."] (6859)
        ["The smiling Purcell answered back..."] (6870)
        ["So high and so mean, so tall and so lean, is my frame..."] (6875)
        ["Some people will be for telling you..."] (6880)
        ["The stately dance yesteren ye led..."] (6814)
        ["The still air sharpened to a blast..."] (6921)
        ["Still to travel, still to go..."] (6923)
        ["Talkers you'll find, all sorts, discreet & witty..."] (6957)
        ["That playthings are better than battles I know..."] (6964)
        ["There was once a woman who was unusually fond of animals..."] (6967)
        ["This was a very pleasant day..."] (6975)
        [A Thought] (6981)
        [To Dig Or Hew, Here Comes a Man] (6995)
        [The Transvaal] (7056)
        [Travel] (7057)
        ["Up in the morn when I rise..."] (7074)
        ["The vagrant foot was dear to me..."] (7079)
        ["A war or even a rebellion..."] (7095)
        ["Well then, the season's over, I suppose..."] (7127)
        ["What I offer here..."] (7135)
        ["When big and strong and wise I grow..."] (7140)
        [Whole Duty of Children] (7158)
        "Windy Nights" (7171)
        ["Wit is of no regard; beauty nor wealth..."] (7175)
        ["The world is so great and I am so small..."] (7182)
        ["Yes I received the book and read..."] (7192)
        ["Yes I remember, still remember wailing..."] (7193)
        ["Yes, it was well, and well ye wrote..."] (7194)
        ["Yes, there exists and has existed..."] (7195)
        ["You must not suppose that a child is a fool..."] (7200)
        [Young Night Thoughts] (7203)
        ["Your book is here, the stars are..."] (7205)
      - "RLS/F/A No. 27A Inland Voyage", undated (Box 38, Folder 851)
        "John Cavalier," poem (6087)
        [Comedies] (6113)
        "Covenanting Profiles," table of contents (6129)
        "Edinburgh Picturesque Notes" (6186)
        "Essays," list (6197)
        [Fables and Tales], essays (6205)
        "The Four Seasons," notes (6241)
        ["Give me your hand, or give me, dear, your heart..."] (6525)
        ["I have a friend, I have a story..."] (6345)
        ["In however small a way a man may be an author..."] (6413)
        An Inland Voyage (6451-6452)
        "The King's Divinity; or the Forest Inn," notes (6481)
        ["Once there was a king..."] (6689)
        ["The others made the profiles..."] (6702)
        [The Rajah's Diamond], table of contents (6748)
        ["Ships upon the ocean..."] (6841)
        "A Song of the Road" (6890)
        [Stories and Essays Published in Periodicals in 1878] (6925)
        [Story of the Merry Monard...] (6929)
        [The Suicide Club], table of contents (6940)
        ["Who would think, herein to look..."] (7157)
      - "RLS/H and No A 262 A", undated (Box 38, Folder 852)
        [Accounts] (5934)
        ["I'm some old prince you figure well..."] (6399)
        "The Law of Obligations," notes (6497)
        [Legal Notes] (6501)
        ["A lodging for the night..."] (6540)
        "Lord Lytton's Fables in Song" (6553)
        "A Martial Elegy for Some Lead Soldiers" (6562)
        ["So, veiled in your loose hair..."] (6878)
        "Style," notes (6939)
      - "RLS/I", undated (Box 38, Folder 853)
        "Deep is the Ocean" (6152)
        [List of Books, Mostly on the History of Scotland] (6529)
      - "RLS/M", undated (Box 39, Folder 854-855)
        "The Bass Rock" (6004)
        ["He was maybe a bit wanting..."] (6283)
        [Sir John Laude of Fountainhall], notes (6495)
        ["To the stormy petrol: or by sea or land..."] (7044)
        [To the Thompson Class Club] (7047)
        ["We knew you better, dear, than you believed..."] (7102)
      - "RLS/P", [circa 1872] (Box 39, Folder 856)
        ["Another spring goes forth with lavish hands..."] (5968)
        ["As Daniel, bird-alone in that far land..."] (5975)
        ["As in the hostel by the bridge, I sate..."] (5977)
        ["As starts the absent dreamer, when a train..."] (5983)
        ["By squall and sudden sunshine..."] (6061)
        ["Calm runs my blood..."] (6063)
        "Consuls. Status of Consuls and Laws Relating to Them," notes (6115)
        ["Fair heart [?,] for that sweet writing of thine..."] (6206)
        ["The fall of dynasties—the glee..."] (6208)
        ["Far up upon the sunlit hill..."], poem (6212)
        ["A garden wall, well rimmed with trees..."] (6249)
        ["Heine has jested by my bed..."] (6306)
        ["I see and envy not..."] (6363)
        "International Law," notes (6458)
        [Legal Notes] (6505)
        ["Little swallows flutter down the sand..."] (6535)
        ["Not undelightful, friend, our rustic ease..."] (6637)
        ["Not yet may scatters primroses be found..."] (6639)
        ["Nursing my troubles, here I sit..."] (6651)
        ["O deeply fallen, sorely hit..."] (6654)
        ["Old Icarus shall secure for me..."] (6672)
        ["One leaf upon the human tree..."] (6692)
        ["Some star to light the... plain..."] (6881)
        ["Strong be his wing and doubly strong his voice..."] (6936)
        ["The strong man's hand, the snow-cool head of age..."] (6937)
        ["These are not unheroic days..."] (6969)
        ["When you and I with quiet hearts..."] (7150)
        ["You know the Pentland Hills that stand..."] (7197)
      - "RLS/S", [1868-1888?] (Box 39, Folder 857)
        ["And, therefore, from mere mortal men..."] (5964)
        [Atheism and Christianity] (5991)
        ["Behold the picture of a lad..."] (6010)
        "Cosmo," table of contents (6122)
        [Dialogue Between S. and M.] (6153)
        [" I lay below the garden wall..."] (6353)
        ["I own young ladies that your rhymes..."] (6357)
        ["I pause at this; because it seems..."] (6358)
        "The Imortelle" (6401)
        ["In sober truth I mean to state..."] (6421)
        [Mathematical and Other Notes Concerning Optics, Harbor Construction, Etc.] (6570)
        ["One likeness still 'tween thine and mine..."] (6693)
        ["Sin, once, was but an empty name to me..."] (6847)
        ["This soul of mine..."] (6974)
        ["When summer waxes over hot..."] (7142)
        [Wood], notes (7178)
      - "RLS/U"
      - "RLS/V", undated (Box 39, Folder 858)
      - "A Winter's Walk in Carrick and Galloway", undated (Box 39, Folder 859)
        [Browning], notes (6055)
        [Criticism], outline (6130)
        [Drinking, Going Tea Total, Etc.] (6168)
        ["I do not make a...at care..."] (6333)
        ["Is this the book you bring..."] (6463)
        ["Lo in the dust with ashes on our hair..."] (6537)
        "A Winter's Walk in Carrick and Galloway," notes (7174)
      - [Untitled], 1872-1874 (Box 39, Folder 860)
        ["Had I the power that have the will..."] (6267)
        ["Hail! childish slaves of social rules..."] (6268)
        ["I am like one that for long days had sate..."] (6328)